Finding Aid for Elizabeth Sparks Adams papers, 1861-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth Sparks Adams papers 1861-2001, 1930-1970s
Adams, Elizabeth S.
1 oversize folders
9.25 linear feet
0344 Aa 2; Ac
Elizabeth Sparks Adams was a member of the Michigan Historical Commission from 1941 (when she was appointed as the first woman commissioner by Governor Murray D. Van Wagoner) until 1996. She and her husband, Judge Donald E. Adams, were also active in the Democratic Party, specifically in Oakland County and Waterford Township. Mrs. Adams also actively researched and collected materials on family and local history. The collection consists of files accumulated throughout her life, particularly during her service with the Michigan Historical Commission and the Michigan Democratic Party. Also included are clippings, correspondence, legal documents, and photographs related to family and local history.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Elizabeth S. Adams (donor no. 857 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, mainly in 2002 and 2004.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Elizabeth (Betty) Sparks Adams was born on December 12, 1911 in Romeo, Michigan. She graduated from Pontiac High School (as valedictorian) in 1930 and received an A.B. from Eastern Michigan University in 1934. She went on to receive an M.A. in history from the University of Michigan in 1935, through a State College Fellowship. While a Research Assistant in 1935, she assisted Professor Lewis G. Vander Velde in establishing a home for the archives of the University of Michigan. She subsequently became the first curator of the Michigan Historical Collections working in that position from 1938 to 1939.
Elizabeth Sparks married Donald E. Adams, an Oakland County attorney and later Judge of Probate, in 1936. Together they have been very active in the Democratic Party on the local and state level. Mrs. Adams was elected Justice of the Peace in Waterford Township in 1943 and was elected to the Waterford Township Board of Education for two terms beginning in 1954, where she served as President for two years.
Mrs. Adams has served on the Michigan Historical Commission since her appointment by Governor Murray D. Van Wagoner on March 20, 1941. During her service there, she was President for 14 years and Vice President for 2 years, and was reappointed every 6 years by succeeding governors. She stepped down in 1995 (but remained active until her successor was appointed in 1996), completing 54 years of volunteer service to the people of Michigan.
Mrs. Adams has also served as president of the Historical Society of Michigan, Oakland County Pioneer and Historical Society, and the Pontiac Y.W.C.A. She has also been an active member of the Oakland County Historical Society, Pontiac Historical Commission, Waterford Township Recreation Board, Commins Restoration Association, Oakland County Chapter of the Michigan Society for Mental Health, Lawyers Wives of Michigan, Oakland County Bar Association Auxiliary, Daughters of the American Revolution, and the Navy League.
During the Bicentennial, Mrs. Adams served on the Oakland County Bicentennial Commission and as chairperson of the subcommittee which published Out of Small Beginnings, a Bicentennial Historical Sketch of Oakland County, MI, 1815-1976. She is listed as a contributor to entries in the Encyclopedia Britannica, Biographical Directory of the Governors of the United States and The University of Michigan, an Encyclopedic Survey.
While she served publicly for many years on the Michigan Historical Commission and in other capacities, Mrs. Adams also privately researched and collected her own family's history. Both she and her husband were born and raised in Michigan and their family histories here dated to the 1800s.
The papers are divided into seven series: Personal Papers, Michigan Historical Commission, Michigan Historical Collections, Miscellaneous, Democratic Party, Compiled Information, and Collected Materials.
Subjects:
Adams, Elizabeth S.; Adams family.; Adams, Jayno W.; Michigan Historical Collections.; Michigan Historical Commission.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Oakland County (Mich.)--History.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Sparks family.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Waterford (Mich.: Township); Women in politics--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers (1 linear foot) include Mrs. Adams biographic information, her awards and appointments, and articles that she wrote. Also included is a set of correspondence with Donald Adams and memorabilia related to their wedding.
  - Articles by ESA (Box 1)
  - Awards, Appointments (Box 1)
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Clippings, Advice on Writing (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Donald to Elizabeth (Don to Betty), 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth to Donald (Betty to Don) (Box 1)
    - Various (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1939 (Box 1)
    (includes some notes about activities at the Michigan Historical Collections)
  - Eastern Michigan University (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Wedding, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Michigan Historical Commission
  Papers from the Michigan Historical Commission (1 linear foot) span almost the length of her tenure there and date from 1942 to 1991. They comprise mostly her correspondence. Notable are the sections on the Munson Fund, Historical Markers, and Governors' Papers.
  - Reappointments 1942-1995 (Box 2)
  - 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - 1945 (Box 2)
  - 1946-1951 (Box 2)
  - 1952-1955 (Box 2)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1971 (Box 2)
    (includes letters regarding: Knights of Pythias at Eagle Harbor)
  - 1956-1957 (staff problems) (Box 2)
  - 1979-1980 (regarding: Berkowitz) (Box 2)
  - 1981-1989 (Box 2)
  - 1990-1995 (Box 2)
  - Munson Fund 1950-1979 (Box 2)
  - Historical Markers 1957-1991 (Box 2)
  - Governors' Papers 1961-1991 (Box 2)
- Michigan Historical Collections
  Correspondence and Mrs. Adams' writings are included in the Michigan Historical Collections (0.4 linear feet) papers. These date from 1935 to 1975.
  - Correspondence undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1937 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1938 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1939 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1940 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1941 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1942-1948 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1961-1987 (Box 3)
  - Writing, Drafts (Box 3)
  - Writings, Printed Material 1936-1974 (Box 3)
  - Writings, Frieze, Haven, Crary, and the Women's Research Club (Box 3)
  - Writings, Tappan (Box 3)
  - Douglas Papers, Correspondence 1941 (Box 3)
  - Douglas Papers, Writings 1941 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, Other Projects and Activities 1938-1975 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous (0.6 linear feet) section is drawn from Mrs. Adam's many activities with other historical societies and her elected duties. These date from 1929 - 1988. Her collection of G. Mennen Williams memorabilia is very personal and moving.
  - Historical Society of Michigan 1964-1966 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Sesquicentennial 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Pioneer and Historical Society; Michigan Historical Collections 1935-1940 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Pioneer and Historical Society 1929-1976 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Records 1945 (Box 3)
  - Waterford Township Board and justice of the peace 1943 (Box 3)
  - Waterford Board of Education 1959-1967 (Box 3)
  - Truman Library Committee 1955 (Box 3)
  - Collected Historical Materials
    - Newsletters, bulletins and clippings 1936-1968 (Box 3)
    - Northwest Territory Celebration Committee 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - G. Mennen Williams career 1940s-1988 (Box 3)
      (includes memorabilia and photograph)
- Democratic Party
  The Democratic Party papers (1 linear foot) are a mixture of both Judge and Mrs. Adams political activities. They date from 1938 to the end of the 1950s. Oakland County and Waterford Township materials dominate. The collection has many original paper ballots and other party memorabilia as well as correspondence.
  - 1938-1939 (Box 4)
  - Young Roosevelt Democrats and misc. party material 1939-1943 (Box 4)
  - 1940 (Box 4)
  - 1941, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1942 (Box 4)
  - 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - 1946 election (Donald Adams) (Box 4)
  - 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - Conventions 1940s-1950s (Box 4)
  - Oakland County Democratic Commission 1939-1950s (Box 4)
  - Oakland County Democratic Women 1940 (Box 4)
  - Oakland County Democratic Women's Division 1940-1951 (Box 4)
  - Waterford Township 1939-1951 (Box 4)
  - Waterford Township 1948-1950 (Box 4)
  - Waterford Township 1952-1957 (Box 4)
- Compiled Information (bound volumes)
  The Compiled Information (2 linear feet) series is comprised of a set of albums that Mrs. Adams assembled. Those related to Mrs. Adams contain biographical information in the form of clippings, correspondence, and photographs. Some also provide useful documentation of the development of the Michigan Historical Collections and Mrs. Adams' service with the department. Those related to family and local history also include clippings, correspondence, and photographs. The Various Families volume contains good information on the history of the Windiate, Earl, and Adams families and how they relate to one another. Historical photographs of family members and family homes are included throughout the volumes.
  - Elizabeth S. Adams
    - Biographical (including awards and interviews) (Box 5)
    - Biographical (including Donald and David Adams) (Box 5)
    - Biographical (including the Michigan Historical Collections and the Michigan Historical Commission) (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (including clippings and journal entries) (Box 5)
  - Family and Local History
    - History of Oakland County Courts (Box 6)
      (clippings, correspondence, and some photographs)
    - Adams Family History (Box 6)
      (clippings, correspondence photographs and important documents)
    - Sparks Family History (Box 6)
      (clippings, correspondence photographs, and narrative family histories)
    - Various Families (Box 6)
      (clippings, correspondence photographs, and family history lists and charts)
- Collected Materials
  The Collected Materials (3.25 linear feet) series represents the family and local history materials that Mrs. Adams collected throughout her life. The majority of the papers relate to Mrs. Adams' family history, a small quantity of papers related to local and state history are also included. The series is divided into three subseries: Family History, Local and State History, and Photographs.
  - Family History
    The Family History subseries (3 linear feet) contains materials about multiple generations of the Adams family and families related to the Adams' through marriage. Within the Adams family materials, clippings and correspondence provide documentation of family relations and important events, such as weddings and promotions. Portions of Jayno Whitmore Adams' (Donald Adams' father) life are highlighted, including his trip to Europe in 1926 and his service as Supervisor of Waterford Township in the early 1900s. The materials on additional families also contain clippings and correspondence that document family relations and important events in individual's lives. The Windiate family, the first of the related families to settle in Michigan, is fairly well documented. Some correspondence of early Michigan and California residents is included.
    - Adams Family
      - Clark, Adeline, Donald, and Elizabeth Adams, Clippings and Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Education (Box 7)
      - Helen Adams (Helen M. Ellis) (Box 7)
      - James Adams (Box 7)
      - Jayno Charles Adams, Sale of Farm (Box 7)
      - Jayno Charles and Helen Adams (Oakland Gazette article) (Box 7)
      - Jayno Whitmore and Blanche Adams
        - Correspondence 1890s (Box 7)
        - Correspondence 1901-1960s (Box 7)
          (Clintonville postmarks included)
        - Correspondence, Various, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Legal Documents (Box 7)
        - Research (Box 7)
      - Jayno Whitmore Adams
        - Correspondence from Donald and Elizabeth Adams 1940s (Box 7)
        - European Trip, Correspondence (Box 7)
        - European Trip, General, 3 folders (Box 7)
          [see also oversize folder]
        - European Trip Photographs (Box 7)
        - European Trip, Postcards (Box 7)
        - Investment Records (Box 8)
        - Research (Box 8)
        - Supervisor of Waterford Township, Construction Contracts (Box 8)
        - Supervisor of Waterford Township, General (Box 8)
        - Supervisor of Waterford Township, Liberty Loan Campaign (Box 8)
        - Waterford Township (District 7) Schools (Box 8)
      - Litigation (Box 8)
    - Various Families
      - Booklets and Pamphlets (Box 8)
      - Diaries, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Earl and Windiate, General (Box 8)
      - Oliver Earl, General (Box 8)
      - Ellis and Kennedy, General (Box 8)
      - Ellis and Windiate, General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Goodale and Riker, Clippings (Box 8)
      - Abbie Harvey, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Heidt
        - Correspondence from Oliver Heidt (Box 9)
        - Letters of Sympathy, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Riker, General (Box 9)
      - Shot Bag from Phoenix Shot Tower Co., Baltimore (Box 9)
      - Wedding Invitations Received, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Windiate
        - Correspondence 1860s (Box 9)
        - General (Box 9)
  - Local and State History
    The Local and State History subseries (0.25 linear feet) focuses on select local organizations in Pontiac. Also included is an original 1875 contract specifying an agreement to fund the construction of the Silver Lake Canal between Silver Lake and Loon Lake, Michigan.
    - Catalogs and Pamphlets (Box 9)
    - Christian Endeavor (Box 9)
    - First Presbyterian Church (Pontiac, Mich.) (Box 9)
    - Oakland County (Box 9)
    - Pontiac Recreation Department, Game Bulletins (Box 9)
    - Pontiac Schools
      - History (Box 9)
      - The Tomahawk (Pontiac Senior High School student publication) (Box 9)
    - Silver Lake Canal Contract (Waterford, Mich.; August 30, 1875) (Box 9)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries (.25 linear feet) contains images related to family, local, and state history. Some photographs include information about the locations and individuals depicted, but many are unlabeled.
    - Adams Family, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Local and State History (Box 10)
    - Unknown (Box 10)
    - Windiate Family (Box 10)